Rafael Lacerda

Toronto, ON, Canada (647) 878-9650 rafaelplmelo@gmail.com https://lacerda.ml

Data Scientist focused on Natural Language Processing. Experienced in research using domain knowledge in Machine Learning systems, as well as development, productionisation and deployment of ML models in distributed architectures.

Experience

Machine Learning Engineer

May 2017 — Feb 2019

Ross Intelligence, Legal Technology

- Developed a state-of-the-art legal research system that surpassed IBM Watson's performance through Deep Learning models and leveraging legal domain knowledge.
- Involved in all stages of Research, Development and Deployment in a distributed architecture.

Treasury Analytics

Aug 2014 — April 2016

OR Investimentos, Real Estate Investment

- Developed Business Intelligence systems for senior management.
- Developed financial risk models to inform cash allocation in potential partner banks.
- Created a system to manage 300+ regional branches' bank balances, saving over 3MM USD monthly by optimizing cash efficiency.

Head of Customer Service

Jan 2013 - Nov 2013

Zocprint, Rocket Internet Startup

- Developed and grew a new data-driven customer service department within the organization.
- Implemented data collection and processes to automatically close the feedback loop to the operations department.
- Hired and managed up to 9 CS agents.

Education

MSc. Applied Computing

Sep 2016 — Dec 2017

University of Toronto

- Natural Language Processing
- Computational Neuroscience
- Probabilistic Learning and Reasoning
- Recipient of 30k Mitacs scholarship (2x terms)

BSc. Economics

Aug 2011 — Jul 2014

Universidade Presbiteriana Mackenzie

- Final thesis on a time series model to measure the effects of uncertainty brought upon by Federal intervention on oil policy.
- 6 month internship at a hedge fund (Kondor Invest, risk office).
- 11 month internship at a B2C startup (Zocprint, operations management).

Skills

Mastered Languages

Knowledgeable in Java

Frameworks

- Python
- R
- SQL
- **VBA**

- Javascript
- Groovy

- Tensorflow
- Keras
- Scikit-Learn
- Pandas

NLP

- Information Retrieval
- Learning to Rank
- Question-Answering
- Summarization

Deep Learning

- ANN
- CNN
- RNN
- GRU
- LSTM
- **Transformers**

DevOps

- **AWS**
- Travis CI
- Docker
- Microservices
- Kubernetes
- Redis
- SOL & NoSOL DBs